A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2000-2006
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2000-2006
The Library of Virginia
42400
4.7 cu. ft (6 boxes)
Virginia Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected information is considered closed for 100 years after date of record creation. Types of records restricted include but are not limited to: Medical information, social security numbers, and employee grievance materials. Restricted information has been sealed, but has not been removed from the collection.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Sandy Thompson, Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 1111 East Broad Street, Room 4082, Richmond, Virginia, 23219, 12 January, 2006.
Historical Information
Finally established in 2004, the eventual creation of the Agriculture and Forestry secretariat began with a 2001 gubernatorial campaign promise made by Governor Mark R. Warner to provide cabinet level representation for the agriculture and forestry industry. Further support for the creation of the secretariat came from the Governor's Agriculture Net Receipts Work Group, a task force created in 2003 by Governor Warner through the Secretary of Commerce and Trade. The goal of the task force was to determine strategies and recommendations for doubling the net profits of Virginia's agricultural sector between 2004 and 2014. Among the task force's recommendations was the creation of the, "Office of Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry to provide focus and emphasis in the development of the agriculture and forest industries." In 2004, the General Assembly of Virginia created the cabinet position of Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry with the passing of Senate Bill SB 543 and witnessed its codification through 2.2-203.3 of the Code of Virginia. Speaking at the appointment ceremony of the first Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, Governor Warner reiterated his commitment to, "support and expand our agriculture and forestry industries" and recalled his desire to, "make sure these very important sectors of Virginia's economy received a seat at my cabinet table."
The Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry is appointed by the Governor, confirmed by the General Assembly, and serves at the Governor's pleasure. It is the secretary's responsibility to oversee several agencies and other entities that formerly reported to the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade. Among the agencies reporting to the Agriculture and Forestry secretariat are the Virginia Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services, the Department of Forestry, the Virginia Agricultural Council, and the Virginia Marine Products Board. The Governor may assign or reassign agencies to and from the Agriculture and Forestry secretariat through the use of executive orders. The secretary's role in leading agencies within the Agriculture and Forestry secretariat is to provide guidance and direction, "in the conservation, protection, and development of Virginia's agricultural and forest resources and in protecting the Virginia Consumer."
In December of 2004, Governor Warner appointed former Delegate Robert S. Bloxom (R-Accomack) to serve as the first Virginia Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry. Prior to his appointment, Bloxom served in the General Assembly from 1978 until his 2003 retirement and sat on the Agriculture, Labor and Commerce, and Chesapeake and its Tributaries committees. William P. Dickinson Jr., Assistant Commissioner of the Virginia Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services, was appointed to serve under Bloxom in the role of Deputy Secretary. On 29 December 2005, Governor-elect Timothy Kaine reappointed Bloxom as Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, and other working papers materials created or sponsored by the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade and the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2000-2006. This collection consists of 14 series of records documenting the activities of the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, as well as the agencies and boards that fall under their control. The agencies represented in this collection were transferred from the control of the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry following Robert S. Bloxom's appointment to the position of Secretary of Agriculture in December 2004. Files created or sponsored by the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade and relating to the transferred agencies were transferred to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Agency Employees on Temporary Assignment to the Offices of the Governor's Cabinet, 2004-2005
Series II: Appointment Calendars, 2005
Series III: Cabinet Meeting Records, 2005
Series IV: Company Files - Prospects and Development, 2002-2004
Series V: Constituent Correspondence, 2004-2005
Series VI: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2000-2006
Series VII: Hiring Requests, 2002-2005
Series VIII: Recognition Requests, 2002-2005
Series IX: Reports and Supporting Documentation, 2001-2005
Series X: Regulation Reviews and Supporting Documentation, 2002
Series XI: Secretary's Website, 2005
Series XII: Special Project Files, 2002-2003
Series XIII: Travel Authorizations, 2002-2005
Series XIV: Virginia Taskforce for Business Development in the Near East, 2005
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Archived website files pertaining to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry (2000-2006) are part of The Library of Virginia's Collection and can be retrieved through a subject search of the library's archival holdings catalog for "agriculture and forestry."
Contents List
- Series I. Agency Employees on Temporary Assignment to the Offices of the Governor's Cabinet, 2004-2005., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1)
  This series contains monthly reports from 2005 regarding employees assigned to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry from agencies under the office's control. Each report includes the employee's name, home agency, the number of days the employee worked, and the project to which he or she was assigned. Many reports record that no agency employees were temporarily assigned to the office for a given month. Also included in this series are two reports from 2004 and 2005 by Sandra D. Bowen, Secretary of Administration, detailing the same information outlined above but for all of the Governor's cabinet secretaries. This series is organized chronologically.
  - Employee Temporary Assignment Reports, January - December, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cabinet Secretaries Reports, 2004-2005. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. Appointment Calendars, 2005., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1)
  This series contains a single appointment calendar book containing the schedule of Secretary Robert S. Bloxom for 2005. It documents the daily appointments of Secretary Bloxom and other members of his office.
  - Appointment Calendar (Robert S. Bloxom), January - December, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series III. Cabinet Meeting Records, 2005., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 1)
  This series contains records relating to Secretary Robert S. Bloxom's participation in Governor Mark R. Warner's cabinet meetings. Records in this series include cabinet meeting schedules annotated by Secretary Bloxom, weekly reports of the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, and notes on topics to be discussed with Commonwealth policymakers both during cabinet meetings and afterwards. The annotated schedules in this series include Secretary Bloxom's thoughts and questions regarding topics brought up during cabinet meetings. Topics of particular interest in this series include the distribution of wine by Virginia wineries and the Small, Women and Minority-owned Businesses (SWAM) procurement initiative, an effort to promote fairness and impartiality in the award of state contracts. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Cabinet Meeting Records, April - December, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series IV. Company Files - Prospects and Development, 2002-2004., Extent: 3 folders. (Folder 1)
  This series contains the monthly business prospect lists submitted to the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade by the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services. Following Robert S. Bloxom's appointment as Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry in December 2004, the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services reported directly to his office. A business prospect list is typically created by a business to document potential clients who might be interested in using a particular product or service. The business prospect lists in this series were created to measure the level of interest individual agribusinesses have in either selecting Virginia as a home or in expanding within Virginia. An agribusiness is a business that derives most of its revenue either directly from agricultural products or from providing products and services to agricultural enterprises. It is part of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services' mission to entice agribusiness to Virginia and to assist agribusinesses interested in moving to or expanding in the Commonwealth by helping them navigate issues of finance, site selection, regulatory law, and resource procurement. Accordingly, every business prospect list in this series records the names of potential agribusinesses interested in moving to or expanding within the Commonwealth, the area to which they wish to relocate, the amount of money they wish to invest in their venture, the number of jobs they will create, the type of project in which they are engaged, their site requirements, the name of the manager assigned to handle their case, their current progress, and any other pertinent notes. Business prospect lists created in 2005 are filed in Series VI: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2000-2006, box 2, folder 12. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Business Prospect Lists, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Business Prospect Lists, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Business Prospect Lists, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series V. Constituent Correspondence, 2004-2005., Extent: 24 folders. (Folder 1)
  This series contains constituent correspondence that relates to the activities of the secretariat or its assigned agencies. The majority of this series is comprised of email, but typed and handwritten correspondence is also included. Most of the correspondence was originally addressed to Governor Mark R. Warner and then rerouted to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry or its assigned agencies. Information regarding each instance of correspondence received by the Governor's office was entered into a database along with notes, assigned a control number (a partial index is available in the library,) and then routed to the appropriate agency for a response. A printout of the database entry created for each piece of correspondence is included with the correspondence for which it was written. In some cases, the notes included in the correspondence database entries speak to the tone of the correspondence and offer suggestions as to how replies should be written.
  This series addresses a broad number of topics including but not limited to consumer complaints against apartment landlords, hospitals, and automobile dealers, letters expressing concern over gasoline prices, calls for legislation regarding issues of agriculture and forestry, letters expressing concern over pesticide usage, letters expressing indignation over the consumption of horse meat, "cold contact" letters offering products and services to the Commonwealth, and letters asking for drought disaster declarations. Further records regarding drought can be found in Series VI: Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2000-2006, box 2, folders 20 and 21, and in Series XII: Special Project Files, 2002-2003, box 5, folders 2-6 and box 6, folder 1.
  One major topic addressed in this series is the regulation of the manufacture, storage, and sale of milk and cheese. The vast majority of the correspondence for January 2005 is from small dairy farmers and dairy enthusiasts regarding the sale of unpasteurized dairy products. The regulations they protest against within the correspondence are State Economic Regulations 2 VAC 5-501 and 2 VAC 5-531, "Regulations Governing the Cooling, Storing, Sampling, and Transporting of Milk" and "Regulations Governing Milk for Manufacturing Purposes," respectively. The regulations require dairy farmers to sell pasteurized products that have been handled according to health regulations set forth by the Commonwealth. Those in opposition to the regulations feel that the equipment required to meet the requirements of the regulations would prove to be cost prohibitive and would drive small dairy farmers out of business. This series is organized chronologically.
  - 2559401 - 2563279, December 2005. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2515089 - 2558680, November 2005. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 2510825 - 2513743, October 2005. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 2508979 - 2510823, October 2005. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 2503795 - 2508974, September - October 2005. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 2498465 - 2503203, September 2005. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 2494400 - 2498081, September 2005. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 2483701 - 2493269, August 2005. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 2476711 - 2483151, July 2005. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 2468047 - 2475457, June - July 2005. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 2441030 - 2465970, April - June 2005. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 2431347 - 2441010, March - April 2005. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 2414571 - 2424891, February - March 2005. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 2406710 - 2414201, February 2005. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 2403798 - 2405794, January - February 2005. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 2403335 - 2403792, January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 2403238 - 2403176, January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 2400742 - 2401380, January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 2399131 - 2400741, January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 2398438 - 2399099, January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 2397902 - 2398436, January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 2396803 - 2397901, January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 2395690 - 2396783, January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 2387620 - 2395401, December 2004 - January 2005. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series VI. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2000-2006., Extent: 118 folders. (Folder 1-4)
  This series is the largest in the collection. It contains correspondence and supporting documentation sent by the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services and the Department of Forestry to either Secretary of Commerce and Trade Michael J. Schewel or Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry Robert S. Bloxom, depending on the date. Control of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services and the Department of Forestry was transferred from the Office of Secretary of Commerce and Trade to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry following the office's creation and the appointment of Bloxom in late 2004.
  This series contains correspondence of various types sent internally (within departments and agencies and then forwarded to the appropriate secretary) as well as external communications sent from private individuals and businesses. Much of the correspondence in this series is not directly addressed to either secretary, but rather lists the appropriate secretary as one recipient among many. Types of materials within this collection include emails, letters, newsletters, reports, and newspaper clippings. Incoming correspondence is filed along with outgoing correspondence and in many cases replies are affixed to the instances of correspondence that sparked them. The physical format of records varies in this series and includes a CD-ROM and a videocassette among the instances of paper correspondence.
  There are a wide variety of subjects addressed in this series. Topics of particular interest to researchers include the use of biodiesel fuels, pesticide usage near schools, and the Small, Women and Minority-owned Businesses (SWAM) procurement initiative. The SWAM records, found in box 2, folder 25, document the office's efforts to promote fairness and impartiality in the award of state contracts. Further topics of interest include land easement agreements, biosecurity, the protection of the Chesapeake Bay, water quality, the reforestation of timberlands, and doubling the net agricultural receipts of Virginia. The records in this series documenting the effort to double Virginia's agricultural receipts, found in box 3, folder 28, will prove to be of extreme interest to researchers interested in the creation of the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry because they document in part a task force created to determine strategies for doubling the net profits of Virginia's agricultural sector. One of their recommendations was the creation of the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry.
  Some topics in this series are also addressed elsewhere in the collection. One such topic is requests for drought disaster declarations as well as the actual declarations themselves. Further information regarding drought disaster declarations can be found within Series V and also within Series XII: Special Project Files, 2002-2003, box 5, folders 2-6 and in box 6, folder 1. Business prospect lists for 2005 are found in this series and, for years prior, in Series IV: Company Files - Prospects and Development, 2002-2004. Similarly, information regarding the secretary's website is included in this series as well as in Series XI: Secretary's Website, 2005.
  The organization of the records in this series reflects the transfer of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services and the Department of Forestry from the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry. Records created prior to the transfer are arranged first by the originating agency and then alphabetically by topic with files marked as general correspondence filed in front of the alphabetical files. It appears that several of the files created by agencies prior to their transfer from the control of the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade have been appended at a later date with the inclusion of records created after their transfer to the Office of the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry. Records created after the December 2004 appointment of Robert S. Bloxom as the Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry are arranged separately but in exactly the same fashion; the post-December 2004 files are organized first by agency and then alphabetically by topic with files designated as general correspondence filed before the alphabetical files. Files created during Bloxom's control of the Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services and the Department of Forestry represent the bulk of this series.
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- General Correspondence, January 2005 - January, 2006. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Abingdon Trip, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agency Heads Meeting, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agency Meeting - 5/6/2005, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agricultural Council, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agricultural Fees, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agricultural Finance Initiative, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agriculture Capital Outlay, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agriculture and Forestry Task Force, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agriculture Month, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agriculture Performance Goals, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Agriculture Summit, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Association of Soil / Conservation, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Audit Standard, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Bees and Beekeeper Assistance and Legislation, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Biodiesel - House Joint Resolution 598, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Biosecurity, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- "Bob" (Robert S.) Bloxom Meeting, 1/3/2005, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Boyd, John - National Black Farmers Association, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Business Prospects, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Chesapeake, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Chesapeake Farm Policy Project, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Clean Fuel Initiative, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Commodity Boards - House Joint Resolution 656, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Congressional Delegation, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Couzins, Bill - Pesticide Spraying Near Schools, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Dairy, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Disasters, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Drought, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Easements, Agriculture / Forestry, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Emergency Operations Plans, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Erosion and Sediment Control / Eastern Shore Resource Conservation Development, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Excels / Small, Women, and Minority-owned Businesses (SWAM) procurement initiative, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Farm Bill- 2007, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Farm Bureau, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Farm Credit, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Farm Service Agency - Culpeper / Orange, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Feed Association, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Financial Statements, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Agriculture and Consumer Services, Department of -- Freedom of Information Act, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 32)